Yes?
Okay.
I am Frans Kasper, I work at Abstraction
Games.
And we recently ported Hotline Miami.
Who is familiar with Hotline Miami?
Who has played it?
Everyone, okay.
I don't have to show it to you.
What about GameMaker?
Have you ever used it?
Are you familiar with it?
And C, C++ programming?
Okay.
Lucky.
Okay, then I will just start with the
presentation.
Yes.
So, Abstraction Games.
We have had one impression.
Abstraction Games.
These are some of the titles we have
recently done.
In the last couple of years.
Some of you may be familiar with them.
Hotline Miami is one of them.
Duke Nukem 3D, we ported it to
PlayStation.
Rogue Legacy is also one of them.
A fairly well-known indie game.
Last month we also released Danganronpa
for PC, Mac and Linux.
Last year we released a title every month,
so we are doing quite a lot.
And we are working
with all the platforms that
are modern, that are
still being used today.
That are being actively developed.
And we are working with several companies.
It is fun and nice in itself,
but what I have already said is
that we have seen quite a
few different projects and things.
We have seen different games, we have
worked with different codes.
And one of the things that
remains from that is that Hotline Miami
has been quite a
technical and interesting project.
And that is why I am going to talk about
that.
Before I get really in-depth about that.
A little overview of how we port.
A little bit of the technology we have
about that.
And what comes with it.
You can do porting in a number of
different ways.
For example, you can make a complete
remake.
That means that you just use the original
game as reference material.
You can maybe use some assets or some
pictures or anything.
And polish something.
But usually this is done for games that
are played on such old hardware.
Or made in such a strange way
that they can not be salvaged.
So you actually have to start from
scratch
and try to get close to the original look.
And then you actually have something.
It is usually quite intensive work.
But sometimes there is
just nothing else you can do
What you can also do is port.
That is what we actually do.
And there you just use the code from the
original game as much as possible .
And all assets and all tools and
everything that comes with it.
To get that working on a different
platform.
That is not always possible.
It can be for example that a game is made
in a tool or a language.
Or something that is not supported on the
platform you wish to port to.
Like for example with
Hotline Miami in this case.
GameMaker did not work on
PlayStation in this case
or on Mac or Linux.
And that means that you have to change the
source code
from one language to another language.
And what you can also do is emulation.
That is almost impossible for most modern
games.
Because emulating has a higher performance
overhead.
You have to make it act it as if you are on a
certain processor.
And then you will actually be playing the
original game.
Wine does not do that.
There are a number of fairly modern games...
... that are ported in this way.
But it is difficult to do that across the board.
And it is often much more performance
intensive.
So what we usually do is ports.
That is where we are specialized.
And where possible, we actually
always try to normalize it first.
And what that kind of entails is...
We actually go for games that...
were created in an engine or
environment that is not supported at all...
... on the platform we want to port to
So, for example GameMaker.
Or just standard C, C++. But designed
without cross-platform in the background.
What we usually do then is normalize it
to our own internal framework we made.
Which is built to run on multiple platforms.
It is fairly low level.
It is about on the same line.
As what you get with normal platform APIs.
And then we port everything there.
And then it eventually turns to our own
technology.
And from there we can go much easier to
other platforms.
But if you have a game for example.
That is made in Unity or in Unreal.
Then that is usually not necessary.
Because that platform itself...
Has relatively good support.
For where you are porting.
And yes.
A kind of subset of the ports that we do.
Are therefore Blackbox ports.
Where actually the total.
Or a part of the port that you do.
Is actually made in a piece of closed
source software.
Where you just don't know.
How exactly it is made.
Or how it is built.
You just don't have complete control.
Or complete insight.
About how that specific part of the game
is made.
And yes.
That is what you have to do sometimes.
For reverse engineering.
You just have to.
There is nothing else to do.
Than just go and look.
Okay how does it work roughly.
And depending on what you can learn from
that.
And yes.
Do something.
To get it to work.
And that is also what we mainly had to do
with Hotmail Miami.
Because it is made in GameMaker.
Which was completely closed source.
Or is.
Even.
And yes.
All those things.
Those are sort of.
Yes.
A bit of the terms that we use.
To say.
The process of.
Okay.
We have a game.
And it is now running roughly.
On another platform.
Where we want to go.
And then there will be more to look at.
Optimization.
And make sure that it runs well.
But at the moment that it sort of.
Runs.
Then we are going to make an adaptation of
it.
And that is actually.
Make sure that.
Outside of the fact that it is technically
correct.
That it will then expand further.
And make sure that it really feels.
As if it belongs to that particular platform.
At the moment that we go to the APC.
Because at the moment we have done that in
Europa.
Then we will make sure that it runs at 60
FPS.
That we have mouse controls for free look.
That kind of thing.
So then we just go as far as possible.
From the things that are for a particular
platform.
Continuously important.
We're going to build over it.
So that it really feels.
As if it is made for that.
And yes.
Our goal.
For example for Hotline Miami, a number of people
actually thought that the game played best on Vita.
And that was not the platform it was originally made for.
So we have been able to add enough value that people thought that.
And we were happy about that.
That is actually what we are trying to achieve if possible.
It does not always work.
But we do our best.
Yes, then Silverware.
That is our own cross-platform technology.
Which I just talked about.
It is in itself quite low level.
Not really a game engine because... it does nothing.
It has no concept of game objects
or animation even, I think.
And it is just a pretty low level SDK.
Which actually is very much like.
For example an open helper.
DirectX.
If you tap on the transmitter.
That looks like an FMOD.
If you tap on the audio.
But it is just.
It lies.
Very close to what you are on.
Each platform.
Individually offered.
Only.
Then it is a kind of.
Yes.
Well.
Within our own control.
And that is then.
Then we can build on all platforms.
Our audio interface.
Yes.
You just write some code.
Against our own audio.
Interface.
And then it works.
On all platforms.
At least that is the idea behind it.
Right.
It is.
It is still in development.
But.
Yes.
That.
It also starts to get better and better.
And it is not only.
Low level stuff.
There are also some high level.
Utility libraries in.
Like for example.
Cloud saving.
Right.
That is in itself.
A high level functionality.
But.
We still offer it.
Because.
Yes.
It is just very handy for us.
To have something in it.
Right.
Because it is.
We can't do it with every game anymore.
And if they can just do it.
Programming.
And it works everywhere.
Then.
Yes.
That is nicely taken.
It becomes a kind of.
Sometimes it becomes a bit of a dump.
For functionality.
That we otherwise.
For every game.
We would have to make.
Yes.
If it is not.
Not specifically.
A high level.
That is no problem.
So.
Yes.
Hop on Miami itself.
It is made in GameMaker.
If you don't know what GameMaker is.
Well.
It is a.
A kind of tool for.
Beginning game development.
It is made for.
In any case.
By.
In children.
Mark Overmars.
Dutchman.
And he really made it.
Mainly.
With the goal.
On education.
To.
Yes.
Actually children.
And.
People.
With no experience at all.
To let them start a bit.
With making games.
The idea was also.
That you.
Let's say.
With your.
Drag and drop.
With your clicking.
And tapping.
That you.
Come somewhere.
That you can make something.
Only.
That is.
Yes.
In the end.
It is also used.
To make more.
Deep.
Games.
Where.
Hotline Miami.
Is one of them.
And that.
Yes.
That went.
Eventually.
Especially.
In the case.
Of Hotline Miami 2.
It really went.
The capabilities.
Of a GameMaker.
Past.
Hotline Miami 2 itself.
Is actually.
Not even.
Playable.
With a GameMaker.
Because he.
It is.
Made.
In GameMaker 7.
That is.
A bit.
An old version.
But.
It is also.
So old.
That they just.
No longer.
Yes.
They can no longer run the game.
They run.
Against.
The 32 bit.
Memory.
Bounding.
And that.
That goes.
Completely wrong.
But.
That is.
Yes.
It is.
A bit.
Expanded.
As Mr. Overmars.
Had provided.
I think.
But.
It is.
Sort of.
A kind of.
And yes.
And what we do.
The.
Yes.
GameMaker.
What.
He actually.
Offers.
As a project.
Is.
In.
One.
Big.
Game.
K.
File.
Is.
Just.
A binary encoded.
File.
Where.
Actually.
Everything.
Is.
So.
All.
Sprites.
Backgrounds.
All.
Information.
From.
Everything.
What.
Happens.
In.
The.
Game.
That.
Case.
And.
That.
Is.
And there.
The.
Very.
Big.
And.
Or.
At.
The.
Main.
Of.
Your.
This is a GameMaker that people were
working on.
It's called Enigma.
It was made in Java.
That was a bit...
I'd rather not call it that, if I can.
It was based on the fact that they wanted
a GameMaker-like interface.
To be able to make the games with it.
More than what we were actually looking
for.
And it wasn't completely complete yet.
But what it did offer was a bit of
documentation.
About how to use the binary format to make
our own tools.
So that's what we did.
We made C-Sharp tools.
C-Sharp is nice to work with, as far as
we're concerned.
Especially for tools that aren't specific
to the cross-platform group.
The code goes away quickly.
So that's pretty relaxed.
And what we did in the first instance
was...
We made a tool that goes through the
binary file.
And tries to get all the assets out of it.
And converts to something that we can use.
So we convert all the images to .png.
Audio files to .wav.
Everything.
In any case, so that we can see what's
exactly in it.
And that we can verify if our approach is
correct.
And what we eventually had with it was...
Well, this is a level from World of
Warcraft 1.
Which then ran in our own environment.
That we just exported out of it.
And for comparison materials.
You can see it in the GameMaker editor.
So it looks a lot like each other.
And that was a good proof of concept.
So we knew we were doing well there.
And the next thing we had to do after
that was... Converting the code itself.
And that was a bit more difficult.
GameMaker has its own... I don't know.
Its own coding language.
It's called GameMaker Language.
And we had to do something with that.
We didn't want to...
We could have built an interpreter.
If we wanted to.
Maybe.
That's also how GameMaker worked at the
time.
Only...
We noticed on PC already.
That just on PC.
The interpreter was already so slow.
That on medium-sized machines.
Sometimes it didn't work at all.
So we actually had a different solution
for that.
And what we actually started doing is...
Just looking to begin with.
Okay, how can we...
In a tool environment...
Understand this language.
And then we can do something with it.
So that we... You know.
Can get to a birth version.
And then we eventually came
up with... Irony.net That is...
In their own words... A development
kit for implementing languages.
Well, that seems straightforward in itself.
For something that makes sense to us.
It was also C-sharp once.
A C-sharp library.
So that... Drives nicely with
the tools we already have.
We can easily connect to it.
And...
Yeah.
It was inside our ballpark.
And the advantage of
that... Is that we can do...
Yeah, you have comparable tools.
Which are the...
Just... Do something
with language parsers.
So that we can do something with them in
the future.
What is often included is... That you
have a separate definition language...
For your grammar.
So you usually have a folder of files...
On which you have to define your grammar.
And then you have a tool.
Uses that file and then generates a
parser.
That in itself is C-code.
So you just connect it and then...
That was a bit of a hassle for us.
Difficult to connect, difficult to
understand and to debug.
And the advantage of Irony was that it had
everything straight up in C-sharp.
And we could easily hang it in our
tool chain.
And what it looks like is that you create
a grammar for a certain language.
In this case it is GameMaker Language.
And you can define statements
by saying that the switch
statement is the word
switch plus the expression.
And some braces, but maybe there is
another expression.
And this is how we built up the whole
grammar.
In the end it is a big file of almost 2000
code rules.
Which tells Irony how GameMaker Language
works.
How it is built up.
And it is still a bit of a nasty material.
I don't know how it was built up.
But I will come back to that in a moment.
And that gave us the basic idea of how the
language works.
And what we could do with it.
If you take a look at...
I will zoom in on this in a moment.
On the right side you see a piece of
GameMaker code.
It looks pretty much the same as on C or
C++.
Pretty straightforward.
And on the right side you see the parse
tree.
Which was generated by Irony.
Thank you.
That might help a little.
And then you can see how it was built up.
It is just a syntactic...
A tree representation of everything that
happens in that piece of code.
And that tells us that it is a function body.
And there is a statement in it.
And that is apparently a variable
declaration.
And there is an identifier and a
semicolon.
So you have...
This is sort of what Irony makes of it.
The moment you have generated the
grammatical plus a piece of code.
Then it makes a sort of tree out of it in
memory.
And that...
It just goes on for a bit of everything.
The same idea for the switch statement.
And the case label.
It is getting a bit more difficult.
And that makes the whole tree in the end.
So this is an abstract syntax tree.
And that is just a representation of the
piece of code in memory.
Where you can do something with it.
Let me see if I can do this.
Yes, okay.
As an example.
Here you have a piece of the...
This is a sort of zoomed out version of
the piece of code.
You have a function body, a switch
statement, a section with a statements list.
And this is a... Yes.
This is a sort of collapsed version of the
complete syntax tree.
Which actually only takes the sort of
nodes.
Which you have specified as oh this is
interesting.
I want something with this.
And for that kind of thing.
For that kind of node.
For which you specify that.
You can write a piece of C sharp code.
Okay good.
As soon as you traverse the tree.
We are just going to walk that tree from
top to bottom.
And you come across a switch statement.
Then... Then you have to
execute this piece of code.
And here you can see that we are just
doing some simple code there.
And eventually a piece of C++ code output.
That is the assignment of that C code
variable at the bottom.
That is actually the output that the node
in the tree is going to generate.
And yes, that is the basis of the setup.
As we call the code conversion.
Then we will just take a quick look.
Yes.
This is just a variable declaration in
GameMaker language.
So that is just var test.
And that output is...
Here you see the output of the C++ code
that we then generate.
And so we actually go through that whole
tree again.
And that is all the same joke.
Most of it is relatively straightforward
to convert to C++.
Of course, we just had to do a number of
things on the C side.
To...
To keep the behavior the same, right?
Because there are still some weird things
happening.
But in general, the syntax looks pretty
much the same.
And yes, you can see here that we have
a...
In this case, we had a sort of instance
var helper for that.
To do a lot of magic.
I'll come back to that in a moment.
But that was kind of the basic setup that
we made.
To just convert the code to a little bit
of C++.
And from there, we started doing all the
further implementation on the C++ side.
To make sure that it just...
Yes, for the rest it just runs like a
GameMaker game.
And that's where we have that GML for.
That's just a class that actually emulates
a variable within GameMaker.
And says, okay, well, I behave in exactly
the same way.
And all the built-in scripts and functions
that are available in GameMaker
we have implemented in C++ ourselves.
Plus all the underlying things that are
needed for that.
So rendering and audio and all those
things.
And then, yes, then it's just...
The moment we've done that, then we can
just convert the code from GameMaker to C++.
And that's just a compiler and debugger,
as you would do with any C++ project.
So there are some weird things in it,
as you may have heard.
It's a GameMaker project.
The GameMaker language is not orthogonal.
What it actually contains is that you can
do the same thing
in a number of different ways in GameMaker
language.
And yes, there are a number of examples of
that.
But what it basically contains is that it
is irritating to work with.
It could be that depending on the code
style of who made the original game
that something works or doesn't work.
Right?
Yes.
Yes, it just makes it a bit more complex.
And there are also complex variables in
it.
For example, if you look at purely the x-
and y-coordinate of an object.
The moment you adjust that, the bounding
box will also be updated.
And the bounding box can now be controlled
and read as a variable.
So just a regular code that says x is 5.
That can do a lot of other things under
the hood.
And those are things that are not
immediately clear.
The moment you look at the language,
they are not documented.
And you just have to find out how to find
out.
And then just fix it.
And the most annoying thing in the whole
GameMaker is with.
Sounds simple, but what it actually does
is you can...
Anywhere in your code you can say,
well, okay, good.
I actually want to execute a piece of code
with that object.
And that code is completely separate from
where that object is defined.
It makes a very large web of vague
dependencies that are very difficult to pull.
And that is mainly difficult for, you know,
just reading the code understandably.
But there were also some technical things
that were a bit tricky.
This is a slightly broader example of a
piece of converted code.
What you see here, for example,
is we have the getSwitchValue.
We had to introduce that fairly recently.
Because another game, for me it was
Cotswim, you didn't use it.
But what you can do in GameMaker is you
can as a switch case value.
You can just have a constant string.
Well, C++ doesn't really do that that fast.
So that's what we made an extra operator
for.
In this case, a hash value return.
Of the actual value.
And that hard code, even though we code
generation here in the C++ code.
A bit tricky, but it works.
And there are, look, you can see here too.
Look, these are four different variable
accesses.
Assignments of variables.
And those are actually different things.
Look, this is a local variable.
Because test is pre-declared here.
And that is in the case of the C++ code.
Also just some local variables.
But you also have variables that belong to
an instance.
So just a member variable of a certain
instance of an object.
Global variables.
And even from an object itself.
So OBA test in this case is the name of an
object.
And if you have a variable of access
there.
What it does then is it looks for the
first instance of that object.
And there it will ask, hey, what is your
test variable by chance?
Again, these are things that are not
really clearly documented anywhere.
And it's just how someone writes their
code.
Whether you're going to run into it or not.
And yes, we've had some trouble with that.
To get it all right.
Yes, this is another piece of example.
This is from the with statement.
Again, here you have a piece of code that
says, yes, with OBA test.
Let's do something, right?
And that is a totally unrelated object.
This code can be everywhere.
And then it knows the same thing.
So in itself it is very handy if you want
to write that code.
It is handy if you know very little about
programming.
Then you can get started here quickly.
And if you just have an indication.
Oh, I actually want to do something with
this object.
Then it's very easy to do.
That's fun.
But the moment you start engineering that
language.
That's less nice.
And what you get there is that.
Yes, what we do is we make a list of all
instances of that object.
And that's where we're going to go.
Because this is also executed for each
instance of that specific object.
Unless you do something else with it.
And then we're going to loop over that.
Right?
And this list that we take here.
The GML instances.
Class.
That is a fairly complex list
implementation.
Because there are all kinds of edge cases.
What happens if you destroy an instance in
the width statement.
Because that can also be done.
And then that list is updated.
And I was doing this at control.
At the conference.
The same talk you did.
And Mark Overmars was there.
He was there.
And he had to laugh quite hard when I
showed this slide.
Because he already knew that he had really
done a lot of shit there.
That was fair.
Because that is.
Yes.
Again, it is very handy to use.
But it is just.
Yes.
There are quite a few vague things
attached to it.
This is.
Yes.
A very good example of complex variables.
Is it a complex variable?
It fits.
Yes.
What we have done for that is.
We have to do something for certain
variables.
Before it is read out.
Or after it is written down.
Because GameMaker is so strange.
Among others, in the case of setting your
x variables.
The bounding box must also be updated.
For Hotline Miami 1 we solved this.
This was solved by using the GML var,
the basic variable class that we use,
to make a virtual class out of it.
And then specialization for certain
things.
That worked in itself, the code was not
very clearly readable anymore,
but it worked.
We shipped Hotline Miami in with that.
Hotline Miami 2 was a lot more
complex than the first one in terms of code.
And it quickly became
clear that it could no
longer work that way
in terms of performance.
We had really overrun too much of
interactions and retable look ups.
That just had to go.
So what we have in place now is,
when we have a variable request that needs
to do something more complex, we return a
temporary instance of a GML instance var.
This is just an object that we instantiate
with some information.
Okay, it's about this and this variable.
This and this instance.
And there, in the constructor and in the
destruct or, or in the changed behavior,
we can execute a lot of logic.
Among other things, in the
case of x, we are going to
call a function that does
both x and the bounding box.
Now we will quickly go to the architecture
of how this was set up.
Again, we have the gmk file here,
which is just the GameMaker source code.
And essence and so on.
Then we have GameMaker.
That is our set of conversion tools that
we use to convert all the code and assets.
And there is also the core simulation.
So there is all the implementation of the
scripts of the GameMaker.
All the logic to execute everything in the
right order.
A placeholder to start an application that
has a window.
Actually, there is more or less the
platform for the speaker.
I'll say that again.
And then for your game,
in this case Hotline Miami 2, you
actually only have your
generated C++ code.
Which is automatically generated.
Because metadata, to send that converter,
all the content that we have converted.
And so tailored scripts.
And that basically means code that we have
to implement differently for our version
of the game than the original GameMaker
version.
They said it because something has to be
tailored.
So we have to show a different picture,
for example.
Because we are running on a console.
Or we have to implement some game pad
controls.
Touchscreen controls.
Anything, right?
We can just do that in there.
And we can just say, okay, well,
this specific script.
We just want to adjust that a little bit.
And we just want to do something different
with it.
And we can just do that on a per-project
basis.
And then we still have Silverware.
That is our platform's specific layer.
Actually, all these things.
So rendering and threading, appflow.
Everything in a kind of
platform-independent way.
In any case, code against each other.
So that we just have to do it once.
Instead of doing it once for each
platform.
Yes, there are a number of things that are
fun in itself.
And a number of things that are a little
less fun.
The advantage is that
we just have complete
control over everything
in the entire pipeline.
From start to finish.
We have no dependence on a YoYo Games.
Or another party that has control over a
project.
Or a piece of software that needs to be
used.
We also do a lot of projects with Unity.
And if we run into a problem there.
Then sometimes it's just okay.
We just have to wait until Unity has fixed
it.
Because we can't do anything about it.
We don't have that here at all.
Because we actually have everything in our
own control.
In addition, we can debug better.
Especially because this was made in
GameMaker 7.
Which had no debug.
As in, not at all.
The only way you can debug there is... Yes, print.
And that leads to a considerable amount of
bugs that were in the original game.
I still have a lot of respect for Jonathan
Soderstrom.
Who made the game.
Who managed to put it together without a
debug.
I don't know how you can do that.
I think it's about 70,000 or 80,000 lines
of code.
I wouldn't be able to do that.
But anyway.
But in the end, the
moral of the story is that
there were some bugs
that he couldn't pull at all.
He just couldn't understand where it came
from.
And because we are just generating C++
code.
We can use all the tools we look at there.
So we can just use the data break point.
Because if this variable changes.
Just the break point.
We can see where it comes from.
And so we can solve quite a few things that
the original developer couldn't fix at all.
Optimization opportunities.
This is more about the fact that we have
full control over the engine under the hood.
Not so much about the fact that we run C++
compared to GameMaker.
But it does mean that we can make texture
atlases.
Make sure that we put everything that is
used a lot in one big texture.
So that we don't have to swap less
textures.
All kinds of optimizations that you can
do.
Again, because you have full control over
the whole stack.
We can do that.
And so if we couldn't do this.
We could have chosen to
port Hotline Miami 2 to GameMaker Studio.
The last variation of GameMaker.
And then try to get that on the console.
But then again.
There are just things you can't do.
Because it is not exposed by that tool.
Or because in some way a strange choice
has been made.
By your original authors.
So it's not possible.
Plus we have made usable technology.
We have used GameMaker for four projects.
Four games I have to say.
Four or five.
And there are still a few coming that we
might do.
It is not complete yet.
But it gets better every time.
We are in a position where we can say.
You have a GameMaker game.
You want to have a platform that is not
supported by GameMaker.
Okay, we can do that for you.
You arrange.
And that is an advantage in itself.
It took a lot of time.
But we have something that we as a company
also have something to do.
The disadvantages.
It took a lot of time.
For example, at MME we really went over
the estimated time.
And it will never be finished.
Really not.
GameMaker itself evaluates that as well.
We still come across things today that
just happen to have a vague code style.
That suddenly throw our converter
tool chain in their face.
In their face.
So that...
It just won't work.
It will never be finished.
And...
Developing in parallel can be a bit
difficult.
Especially in the case of Hotline Miami 2.
The guys at Dennaton were still working
on finishing the game.
While we were already on board.
And...
That is more because of GameMaker.
The fact that this is difficult.
But...
GameMaker is one big binary file.
You can't easily control that.
You're going to have problems with that.
We have done a lot to fix that.
Among other things.
We export everything to plain text.
When we convert the code.
And that... At least we have a version
control history of what has changed.
And... We have thrown a number
of hacks into the converter tool chain.
So that we can put code in the GameMaker
editor.
Which is only executed on our side of the
game.
And GameMaker itself just denies that.
And we have been able to fix some
problems.
Which we had with Hotline Miami 1.
With Hotline Miami 1 we got the project
file.
And...
Success if you don't want to run it in
GameMaker itself.
Because we had to fix so much.
And a lot of hacking to get it working.
That was just not possible.
Hotline Miami 2 is still running.
Not good.
Because...
It goes against the limits of GameMaker itself.
But...
In itself the code is still correct.
And it still works a little bit.
And...
It is just...
Complex.
The whole tool chain is complex.
It is...
Difficult to... To... To... To... To
involve someone on such a project.
Because... It has a very
big stack of different things.
Which are very difficult to get running.
And you have to know a bit of everything.
If you want to work on such a project.
And I am actually the only
one... Who has done a lot with it.
And every time there is a project going on
with GameMaker.
Then I get called back.
Hey, come and help me.
Because I don't understand it.
You know.
So that is a bit of a disadvantage.
To have such an approach.
Yes.
If you ever start making games again.
Please use...
The right tools for the job.
If you know that you are making a game.
That you might want to bring to a console.
Then don't take an old version of
GameMaker.
Take a new one.
Take Unity.
Take Unreal.
Anything, right?
And if you ever start your own game.
Or your own engine.
Or anything.
If you have aspirations for that.
Or anything that you actually want to
have.
A cross-platform.
Then it makes sense to normalize that.
To actually...
Purely the concept of a platform.
To abstract that.
And code against that.
So that you can go much easier from there.
To all kinds of other platforms.
And can fix things.
That is about it.
If you have any questions.
Or visuals of the becoming of You are
back.
We must come back.
A little bit of everything.
Things like when we are going to connect
touch screen controls
we are going to do that partially in
GameMaker.
Because there we have pieces of... there
is some code that controls the camera,
and we have to be able to control it with
a touch pad.
So there is always something in it.
On the other hand, on the Cephs Plus
side
we have implemented things like cloud
saving, leader boards, things like that.
So it is always a bit of a mingle of
things where it happens.
For example, we have to optimise a lot
with the Cephs Plus 2.
It is also a sort of tailoring, right?
To make sure that it runs on a good frame
rate.
And that happens with the Cephs Plus.
It also happens that we convert a piece of
GameMaker code
to C++, purely to get the extra
performance.
And not even to change logic-wise.
Yes, I don't know.
A few years ago, GameMaker already sold
it.
So it doesn't work actively anymore.
It was... Yes, it was...
Sporty, let's say.
It was fun.
It was just a bit... My
presentation was over.
I had a psycho psychotic room.
And he also had a presentation afterwards.
And he just stood there and walked away.
That was a bit...
Do you have anything else?
Yes, that is very different per project.
In the case of the Hotline Miami 1...
I think we have been working with...
I would say three people for almost a
year.
And at Hotline Miami 2... We
are also in that direction a little bit.
That could have been shorter.
But for Hotline Miami 2 we have to
change a lot... of things at the bottom.
We have changed from engine.
We started using our own technology.
But most of the time... most of
what we see with projects that we do
most of it depends on projects.
But mostly for half a year and one and a
half year.
That does differ slightly per project.
At least the way we work.
We actually always try to find a solution
that works for everyone.
Some projects have an original developer
who says, you know what, go and solve it.
It doesn't matter anymore, I can already
see that the product is ready.
That was Hotline Miami 1 for the most
part.
And actually only when everything was
running a bit, about a year and a half
after the project started, we went to
Derrent and said, here you have the picture.
Can you take a look at what we want to
change and so on and so forth.
At Hotline Miami 2 we have been very
active with our people.
Usually we had contact a couple of times a
week.
And we also helped to solve problems.
And that really makes a difference for the
project.
Personally, I do like to be in contact with the original developers
as much as possible.
If they need that, then I would be happy
to do that.
Do you use the bug fixes or the
streamcams?
Yes, sometimes.
It depends.
In the case of Hotline Miami...
source control... those guys don't understand that.
They don't do that.
So what we do is, we get that file in and
we convert it.
And we have to do a couple of things with
our patch and we just send that file back.
It's a bit spartan, but that happens in
the case of Hotline Miami.
I think mostly in projects
that are still in active
development, then it
sometimes goes back to stream.
If that's possible.
Do you have anything else to add?
It's hard to say.
Look, I think that in
the end it doesn't really
matter to us what kind of technology it is.
I prefer to look at whether we like a
game, at least personally.
If I like a game, then
I'm more inclined to go
lobby and say, hey, can
you please report that?
If it's GameMaker, I wouldn't say no
because it's GameMaker.
I wouldn't say, oh, we already have this
technology, so it's only
five minutes to work.
That's the whole point.
That's a bit of a shame, but in the end we
want to do that, maybe.
But that also depends a lot on the future
of GameMaker itself.
YoYo Games has recently
been sold to a Korean
company, which mainly
makes casino games.
So it could be that their entire support
department will no longer exist in a year.
And that we still have a long list of
people who were making GameMaker games,
who were actually supporting them
somewhere.
We'll have to see how that goes.
Is the performance of the final port you
have better?
Yes, much better.
The original developer has said,
we're going to use GameMaker: Studio soon.
And that works on the best platforms.
But we would like to work with you for the
ports and run on your engine.
Because it runs a lot smoother and better.
So the running of the game is now on their
own, or on GameMaker's?
No, it runs on ours.
Okay.
Yes.
Yes, yes, yes.
No, no.
The Hotline Miami 2 certainly not.
They really couldn't bring us out with.
GameMaker itself,
because it was just too much.
Hotline Miami 1 we eventually also
updated.
And now we have a launcher
where you can still select the
old version, if you happen to
have problems with our version.
Gunpoint is also a 2D game made with
GameMaker.
We also updated it with our version.
And then we have Gods Be Watching.
That is also a 2D point-and-click game,
which we then ported to Android and iOS.
It is no longer purely ported,
but actually part of the development.
Yes.
It is very specific.
And we also have...
Yes, it is a bit of a niche.
That is true.
We do have competition.
I would not say that we are the only
people who do these kinds of things.
And sometimes it can be difficult to find
a job.
But that just depends on it.
Look.
You will always have people who... Yes.
Who are more independent, right?
People who are not so
technically trained, but
who are still very
creative to make a game.
And they can make a game.
They can release it on Windows.
And it has all become very low-key
nowadays.
But if you want to have that
on a console, because you
want more exposure, or
because you just want to see it.
Apart from the fact that you might be able
to do it relatively easily with a Unity or
a Unreal, there are still a
lot of people who say, well,
yes, but I am not interested
in that technology at all.
So I will look for another party for that.
So I think there is still work to be done
in the meantime, until we ever come to a
point where port is completely no longer
needed.
Because it has just been solved in one way
or another that our work is redundant.
Well fine, we'll do something else.
That will be fine.
Cool bugs.
No, nice ones.
Oh, nice ones.
How many times did you play Suivlacks?
More than enough.
It's difficult to say.
I would like to say something specific.
I think with Hotline, what was a constant
problem there was that, especially with.
Hotline Miami 2, we have 8 or 9 different characters
and then 11 and a half different enemy factions
and that is all made by someone
who can't debug and all of that has
to be fixed in his head so there are
quite a few things that have come out,
but oh, but if I hit that
enemy with this character, with
this weapon, that crashes the
game or something goes wrong.
That's where the numbers have come from,
so to speak.
It's really a nice bug hunt.
Well, we do indeed have Rogue Legacy,
which is a 2D rogue like, which we ported.
I think we just used an existing random
implementation of X and A in this case.
And I think we just reverse-engineered it
or searched for which random uses X and A
specifically, and that's actually just the
new one.
As long as you, at least if your
procedural game has been well set up to
begin with, right, then you
just have to get the same
result with the same random
generator and the same seed.
So we didn't have any specific problems
with that or anything like that.
Okay, thank you.